<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- This is an automatically generated file. -->
<Chapter Label="Chapter_Introduction">
<Heading>Introduction</Heading>

<P/>
 Let <Math>\Omega</Math> be a set of cardinality <Math>d\in\mathbb{N}_{\ge 3}</Math> and let <Math>T_{d}=(V,E)</Math> be the <Math>d</Math>-regular tree. We follow Serre's graph theory notation <Cite Key="Ser80"/>. Given a subgroup <Math>H</Math> of the automorphism group <Math>\mathrm{Aut}(T_{d})</Math> of <Math>T_{d}</Math>, and a vertex <Math>x\in V</Math>, the stabilizer <Math>H_{x}</Math> of <Math>x</Math> in <Math>H</Math> induces a permutation group on the set <Math>E(x):=\{e\in E\mid o(e)=x\}</Math> of edges issuing from <Math>x</Math>. We say that <Math>H</Math> is locally "P" if for every <Math>x\in V</Math> said permutation group satisfies the property "P", e.g. being transitive, semiprimitive, quasiprimitive or <Math>2</Math>-transitive.
 In <Cite Key="BM00a"/>, Burger-Mozes develop a remarkable structure theory of closed, non-discrete, locally quasiprimitive subgroups of <Math>\mathrm{Aut}(T_{d})</Math>, which resembles the theory of semisimple Lie groups. They complement this structure theory with a particularly accessible class of subgroups of <Math>\mathrm{Aut}(T_{d})</Math> with prescribed local action: Given <Math>F\le\mathrm{Sym}(\Omega)</Math> their universal group <Math>\mathrm{U}(F)</Math> is closed in <Math>\mathrm{Aut}(T_{d})</Math>, vertex-transitive, compactly generated and locally permutation isomorphic to <Math>F</Math>. It is discrete if and only if <Math>F</Math> is semiregular. When <Math>F</Math> is transitive, <Math>\mathrm{U}(F)</Math> is maximal up to conjugation among vertex-transitive subgroups of <Math>\mathrm{Aut}(T_{d})</Math> that are locally permutation isomorphic to <Math>F</Math>, hence <E>universal</E>.
<P/>
 This construction was generalized by the second author in <Cite Key="Tor20"/>: In the spirit of <Math>k</Math>-closures of groups acting on trees developed in <Cite Key="BEW15"/>, we generalize the universal group construction by prescribing the local action on balls of a given radius <Math>k\in\mathbb{N}</Math>, the Burger-Mozes construction corresponding to the case <Math>k=1</Math>. Fix a tree <Math>B_{d,k}</Math> which is isomorphic to a ball of radius <Math>k</Math> in the labelled tree <Math>T_{d}</Math> and let <Math>l_{x}^{k}:B(x,k)\to B_{d,k}</Math> (<Math>x\in V</Math>) be the unique label-respecting isomorphism. Then <Display>\sigma_{k}:\mathrm{Aut}(T_{d})\times V\to\mathrm{Aut}(B_{d,k}),\ (g,x)\to l_{gx}^{k}\circ g\circ (l_{x}^{k})^{-1}</Display> captures the <E><Math>k</Math>-local action</E> of <Math>g</Math> at the vertex <Math>x\in V</Math>.
<P/>
 With this we can make the following defintition: Let <Math>F\!\le\!\mathrm{Aut}(B_{d,k})</Math>. Define <Display>\mathrm{U}_{k}(F):=\{g\in\mathrm{Aut}(T_{d})\mid \forall x\in V:\ \sigma_{k}(g,x)\in F\}.</Display>
<P/>
 While <Math>\mathrm{U}_{k}(F)</Math> is always closed, vertex-transitive and compactly generated, other properties of <Math>\mathrm{U}(F)</Math> do <E>not</E> carry over. Foremost, the group <Math>\mathrm{U}_{k}(F)</Math> need not be locally action isomorphic to <Math>F</Math> and we say that <Math>F\le\mathrm{Aut}(B_{d,k})</Math> satisfies condition (C) if it is. This can be viewed as an interchangeability condition on neighbouring local actions, see Section <Ref Sect="Section_condition_C"/>. There is also a discreteness condition (D) on <Math>F\le\mathrm{Aut}(B_{d,k})</Math> in terms of certain stabilizers in <Math>F</Math> under which <Math>\mathrm{U}_{k}(F)</Math> is discrete, see Section <Ref Sect="Section_condition_D"/>.
<P/>
 <Package>UGALY</Package> provides methods to create, analyse and find local actions <Math>F\le\mathrm{Aut}(B_{d,k})</Math> that satisfy condition (C) and/or (D), including the constructions <Math>\Gamma</Math>, <Math>\Delta</Math>, <Math>\Phi</Math>, <Math>\Sigma</Math>, and <Math>\Pi</Math> developed in <Cite Key="Tor20"/>. This package was developed within the <URL Text="Zero-Dimensional Symmetry Research Group"> https://zerodimensional.group/"</URL> in the <URL Text="School of Mathematical and Physical Sciences"> https://www.newcastle.edu.au/school/mathematical-and-physical-sciences</URL> at <URL Text="The University of Newcastle"> https://www.newcastle.edu.au/</URL> as part of a project course taken by the first author, supervised by the second author.
</Chapter>

